Guide to the Beyond the Pale Records TAM.718
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Beyond the Pale Records
1995-2014
1967-2019
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Neimark, Marilyn Kleinberg
Kaplan, Esther
Beyond the Pale (Radio program)
TAM.718
17.25 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons, 20 cassette boxes, 8 CD boxes, 2 LP boxes, and 1 half manuscript box.
256 Gigabytes in 603 computer files.
394 audiocassettes
273 sound cassettes (dat)
83 sound tape reels
279 sound discs (minidisc)
1 websites in 1 archived website.
Beyond the Pale was a weekly radio program produced and hosted by Esther Kaplan and Marilyn Kleinberg Neimark on New York's WBAI Radio, part of the Pacifica Radio Network. The show ran from 1995 to 2014 and engaged in local, national, and international political debate and analysis, and explored the arts and cultural trends from a progressive, Jewish perspective. The Beyond the Pale Records contain audio recordings from the radio program, and include an archived version of their website (https://www.beyondthepale.org), audiocassettes, ¼-inch audio reels, DATs, MiniDiscs, and CD-Rs of air-checks, event documentation, and source material. Materials in the collection date from from 1967-2019 with the bulk of materials dating 1995-2014. The radio show featured interviews with, and speeches and readings by, public figures; recordings of events; and discussions about contemporary political, social, and cultural issues impacting Jewish communities in the United States and abroad.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Esther Kaplan and Marilyn Kleinberg Neimark in 2017. The accession number associated with this gift is 2017.033.
In 2019, https://www.beyondthepale.org/ was added to the web archive and captured through the use of Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. The accession number associated with this website is 2019.144.
In 2020, cassettes 718_1007 and 718_1008 were reported as missing.
Arrangement
Materials are intellectually arranged chronologically by year. Materials are physically arranged by format, and then chronologically by year.
Historical Note
Beyond the Pale was a radio program produced and hosted by Esther Kaplan and Marilyn Kleinberg Neimark on New York's WBAI Radio, part of the Pacifica Radio Network. The show ran steadily from 1995 to 2014 and explored local, national, and international political debate and analysis from a Jewish perspective. Produced with the support of the New York City-based Jews for Racial and Economic Justice (JFREJ), Beyond the Pale included discussions on contemporary Jewish culture from a leftist perspective with writers, filmmakers, musicians, critics, and political organizers.
Scope and Contents
The Beyond the Pale Records contains an archived website, audiocassettes, ¼-inch audio reels, DATs, MiniDiscs, and CD-Rs of Beyond the Pale audio recordings, which include air-checks, recordings of live broadcasts, events, and audio used as source material. Materials in the collection date from from 1967 to 2019 with the bulk of materials dating 1995-2014. The recordings in this collection document the discussions and debates surrounding both major world events and events in the history of progressive Jewish activism for nearly 20 years. The episodes cover Jewish culture, politics, and social issues, and though the programs are generally based on progressive concerns, the opinions expressed on the program represent viewpoints from not only the political left, but the right as well. Many programs focus on issues surrounding the Middle East conflict, U.S.-Israel and U.S.-Palestinian relations, and the recordings document the development of these issues over nearly two decades. There are interviews with many significant artists, scholars, activists, and politicians, such as Grace Paley, Adrienne Rich, Dr. Ruchama Marton, Michel Warschawski, Rabbi Arthur Waskow, Dr. Tal Jarus-Hakak, and others. The program covered discussions on many contemporary subjects within the American Jewish community including domestic abuse, LGBTQ issues, Jewish identity, the prison-industrial complex, and Jews and the religious right. The radio program also explored a number of historical events and their impacts on the present, such as the history of Jewish involvement in radical politics and labor activism, the trial and execution of Ethel and Julius Rosenberg, Jewish life in Eastern Europe and the USSR, and the Ocean Hill-Brownsville battle over community control of public schools in the late 1960s. Frequent contributors to and co-hosts of the program include Henry Foner, Melanie Kaye/Kantrowitz, Nan Rubin, Alisa Solomon, Josh Nathan-Kazis, and Abe Velez. Besides the October 2019 capture of the Beyond the Pale website (https://www.beyondthepale.org), there are additional captures by the WayBack Machine between 2008 and 2018.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Appraisal
During processing in 2019, three optical discs were found to be unreadable and discarded.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Community radio; Jews -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Judaism -- United States -- History.; Audiotapes.; New York (State) -- Politics and government.; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government.; Politics and culture.; Arab-Israeli conflict.; Neimark, Marilyn Kleinberg; Kaplan, Esther; Pacifica Radio
- Abba Eban; Tom Segev B'nai Jeshurun [1967-002], 1967 June 6; 2007 June 6 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_718_ER_1)
- Heschel on War [1973-001], cuid33681 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0001)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Duration: 0:02:08, Preservation Notes: Side B is Blank; Program Distorted at Times; High Amount of Buzz During Program; Static During Program; Right Channel Interference During Program
- Studs Terkel Interview; 1963, 1973 Specials [1973-002], cuid33682 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0002)
  Duration: 2:06:42, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; High Amount of Hiss During Program; Side B: Program in Silence From 00:25:30 Until 00:32:04
- Studs Terkel with Meridel Le Sueur, Reel 1 [1982-002], 1982-03-30; cuid33683 (Box 24, Reel 718_0997)
  Duration: 0:27:48, Preservation Note: Static During Program; Clicks and Pops During Program
- Studs Terkel with Meridel Le Sueur, Reel 2 [1982-001], 1982-03-30; cuid33684 (Box 24, Reel 718_0996)
  Duration: 0:23:38
- Kung Pao Kosher Comedy - Audio Clips [1994-003], cuid33685 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0003)
  Duration: 0:18:55, Preservation Note: Side B is Blank; Program Distorted at Times; High Amount of Hiss During Program; Static During Program; High Amount of Buzz During Program; Phasing During Program; Warble During Beginning of Program; Interference During Program
- W.H. Kunstler Acceptance Speech [1994-001], 1994-06-01; cuid33686 (Box 21, Reel 718_0926)
  Duration: 0:10:41, Preservation Note: High Amount of Hiss During Program; Static During Program; Phasing During Program
- Richie Perez Breaking Bread [1994-002], 1994-06-01; cuid33687 (Box 21, Reel 718_0927)
  Duration: 0:15:31, Preservation Note: Static During Program; Program Distorted at Times; Phasing During Program
- Ruchama Marton Psychology [2015-001], circa 1995-2007; cuid33688 (Box 23, Reel 718_0990)
  Duration: 0:09:16, Preservation Note: Static During Program; Program Distorted at Times; High Frequency Background Noise During Program
- Adrienne Cooper "I'm Not Afraid" [2015-002], circa 1995-2008; cuid33689 (Box 23, Reel 718_0991)
  Duration: 0:03:12
- Teach-In [1995-019], 1995-02-05; cuid33690 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0022)
  Duration: 1:23:02, Preservation Note: High Amount of Buzz During Program; Dropouts During Program; Program Distorted at Times; Static During Program
- Tony Kushner Reading; Cong. Jerrold Nadler on New Congress; Ruchama Martin Interview [1995-001], 1995-03-01; cuid33691 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0004)
  Duration: 0:56:58, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Side A: Right channel drops out from approximately 00:19:42 until 00:22:33; Audible Print-through During Program
  Scope and Contents
  Duplicate of 718_0041
- Tony Kushner Reading; Cong. Jerrold Nadler on New Congress; Ruchama Martin Interview [1995-038], 1995-03-01; cuid33692 (Box 2, Audiocassette 718_0041)
  Duration: 0:56:16, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; No Right Channel From 00:03:54 Until 00:04:44 on Side B During Program
  Duplicate of 718_0004
- Women's History [1995-002], 1995-03-15; cuid33693 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0005)
  Duration: 0:52:58, Preservation Note: Static During Program; Program Distorted at Times; High Amount of Buzz During Program; Audible Print-Through During Program
  Duplicate of 718_0030; 718_0042
- Aircheck [1995-027], 1995-03-15; cuid33694 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0030)
  Duration: 0:53:04, Preservation Note: Static During Program; Program Distorted at Times
  Duplicate of 718_0005; 718_0042
- Women's History [1995-039], 1995-03-15; cuid33695 (Box 2, Audiocassette 718_0042)
  Duration: 0:52:25, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Static During Program
  Duplicate of 718_0005; 718_0030
- Jews for Racial and Economic Justice (JFREJ) [1995-003], 1995-03-21; cuid33696 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0006)
  Duration: 0:58:12, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Static During Program; Side A: Warble During End of Program
  Duplicate of 718_0007
- Jews for Racial and Economic Justice (JFREJ) [1995-004], 1995-03-21; cuid33697 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0007)
  Duplicate of 718_0006
- The Struggle to Save the City University of New York Show (CUNY Budget Cuts) [1995-026], 1995-03-21; cuid33698 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0029)
  Duration: 0:58:20, Preservation Note: Static During Program; High Amount of Hiss During Program; Program Distorted at Times
  Duplicate of 718_0023, 718_0043
- The Struggle to Save the City University of New York (CUNY Show) [1995-040], 1995-03-21; cuid33699 (Box 2, Audiocassette 718_0043)
  Duration: 0:59:24, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times
  Duplicate of 718_0023, 718_0029
- The Struggle to Save the City University of New York Show [1995-021], 1995-03-21; cuid33700 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0023)
  Duration: 0:58:04, Preservation Note: Phasing During Program; Program Distorted at Times; Dropouts During Program
  Duplicate of 718_0029, 718_0043
- Progressive Jewish Radio Hour: Passover Show [1995-018], 1995-04-12; cuid33701 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0021)
  Duration: 0:57:13, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Phasing During Program; Static During Program
  Duplicate of 718_0032, 718_0034, 718_0050
- Ma'yan Women's Seder, Tape 1, 1995-04-12; cuid33702 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0026)
  Duration: 1:22:50, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Static During Program
  Related to 718_0021, 718_0032, 718_0034, 718_0050
- Ma'yan Women's Seder, Tape 2 [1995-024], 1995-04-12; cuid33703 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0027)
  Duration: 1:14:23, Preservation Note: Static During Program; Program Distorted at Times
- Passover Show [1995-025], 1995-04-12; cuid33704 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0028)
  Tape not digitized because it was blank: Tape is Completely Blank - No Digital Files Created
- Passover Show [1995-029], 1995-04-12; cuid33705 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0032)
  Duration: 0:57:18, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times
  Duplicate of 718_0021, 718_0034, 718_0050
- Passover Show [1995-031], 1995-04-12; cuid33706 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0034)
  Duration: 0:56:34, Preservation Note: High Amount of Hiss During Program; Program Distorted at Times; Static During Program
  Duplicate of 718_0021, 718_0032, 718_0050
- Passover Show [1995-047], 1995-04-12; cuid33707 (Box 2, Audiocassette 718_0050)
  Duration: 0:57:34, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Static During Program
  Duplicate of 718_0021, 718_0032, 718_0034
- Yom Hashoah [1995-008], 1995-04-19; cuid33708 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0010)
  Duration: 0:58:39, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times
- Ruth Rubin Young and Hym [1995-023], 1995-04-19; cuid33709 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0025)
  Duration: 1:31:41, Preservation Note: High Amount of Hiss During Program; Speed Fluctuations During Program; Program Distorted at Times; Phasing During Program; Clicks and Pops During Program; Warble During Program
  Related to 718_0928
- Ruth Rubin Songs [1995-023], 1995-04-19; cuid33710 (Box 21, Reel 718_0928)
  Duration: 0:04:39, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Static During Program; Phasing During Program
  Related to 718_0025: Edited cut of final 15 minutes of 718_0025.
- Jews and the Christian Right [1995-009], 1995-04-26; cuid33711 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0012)
  Duration: 0:59:47, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times
- Jews and the Radical Right [1995-007], 1995-05-07; cuid2619 (Box 1, Item 718_0011, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_718_ER_617)
  Jews and the Radical Right (2) [A] Slide Show: Andy Stettner & Sandi DuBowski (Stettner - People for the American Way; DuBowski - Public Policy Institute of Planned Parenthood) Q&A [B] Manhattan Borough President Ruth Messinger; State Assemblywoman Deborah Glick
  Original Format: Audio Cassette, Duration: 90 min.
- Jews and the Radical Right [1995-041], 1995-05-07; cuid2620 (Box 2, Item 718_0044, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_718_ER_618)
  Jews and the Radical Right: Daniel Levitas (cont.)-Ctr for Democratic Renewal, Lawrence Cohler- Jewish Week,
- Jews and the Radical Right [1995-042], 1995-05-07; cuid33712 (Box 2, Audiocassette 718_0045)
  Duration: 1:00:37, Preservation Note: High Frequency Noise During Program; Program Distorted at Times; Phasing During Program
- Yiddish Revival [1995-045], 1995-05-31; cuid33713 (Box 2, Audiocassette 718_0048)
  Duration: 0:59:04, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times
- Israel and Status of the Peace Process [1995-046], 1995-06-07; cuid33714 (Box 2, Audiocassette 718_0049)
  Duration: 1:01:07, Preservation Note: Static During Program; Program Distorted at Times
- Labor Issues [1995-012], 1995-06-28; cuid33715 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0015)
  Duration: 0:59:46, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times
- Fascism in Europe [1995-020], 1995-07-05; cuid33716 (Box 1, Item 718_1007)
- Newt Gingrich at the 92nd Street Y [1995-013], 1995-07-12; cuid33717 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0016)
  Duration: 0:57:43, Preservation Note: Static During Program; Program Distorted at Times
- Mizrahi Jews [1995-014], 1995-07-19; cuid33718 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0017)
  Duration: 0:57:02, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times
- Jews and Sexuality [1995-043], 1995-09-06; cuid33719 (Box 2, Audiocassette 718_0046)
  Duration: 1:01:25, Preservation Note: Channel Imbalance; Static During Program; Program Distorted at Times
- Holocausts Panel at Brecht Forum [1995-016], 1995-09-09; cuid33720 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0019)
  Duration: 1:28:32, Preservation Note: Phasing During Program; Static During Program
- Readings and Performances: Judith Sloan, Tony Kushner, and Grace Paley [1995-010], 1995-10-01; cuid33721 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0013)
  Duration: 0:44:49, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; High Amount of Hiss During Program; Channel Imbalance; Static During Program
- Board of Education and Chancellor Search [1995-037], 1995-10-08; cuid33722 (Box 2, Audiocassette 718_0040)
  Duration: 1:06:36, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Static During Program; Interference During Program
- Gay and Lesbian Jews [1995-011], 1995-10-11; cuid33723 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0014)
  Duration: 1:00:24, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Static During Program; High Amount of Buzz During Program
- Jewish Radical Education Program with Mordechai Levy and John Ranz [1995-005], 1995-10-15; cuid33724 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0008)
  Duration: 1:22:38, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Warble During Program; Speed Fluctuations on Tape; Static During Program
- Gertrude Stein: Buffie Johnson, Eileen Myles, Maria Damon, and Charles Bernstein [1995-033], 1995-10-15; cuid33725 (Box 2, Audiocassette 718_0036)
  Duration: 0:50:18, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Static During Program
- Christian Coalition Conference; Million Man March [1995-017], 1995-10-22; cuid33726 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0020)
  Duration: 0:58:50, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; No Left Channel Until 00:00:17 on Side A
  Duplicate of 718_0039
- Richard John Neuhaus and Ismar Schorsch Lecture: "One Nation Under God: The Role of Religion in the Public Square" [1995-028], 1995-10-26; cuid33727 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0031)
  Duration: 1:32:42, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times
- Women and Yiddish Conference: Irena Klepfisz and Frieda Forman, Tape 1 [1995-006], 1995-10-28; cuid33728 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0009)
  Duration: 0:47:27, Preservation Note: Side B is Blank; Program Distorted at Times; Static During Program; Phasing During Program
  Related to 718_0024
- Women and Yiddish Conference: Performances by Adrienne Cooper et al, Tape 2 [1995-022], 1995-10-29; cuid33729 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0024)
  Duration: 0:47:42, Preservation Note: Side B is Blank; Program Distorted at Times
  Related to 718_0009
- A: Christian Coalition Conference; Million Man March / B: Israel Film Festival; Women and Yiddish Conference [1995-036], 1995-10-29; cuid33730 (Box 2, Audiocassette 718_0039)
  Duration: 1:50:10, Preservation Note: Static During Program; Program Distorted at Times
  Duplicate of 718_0020
- William Kristol and Leonard Fein on Socioeconomic Problems [1995-032], 1995-11-09; cuid33731 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0035)
  Duration: 1:33:20, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Phasing During Program; Static During Program; Low Right Channel From 00:03:55 Until 00:22:06 and From 00:39:29 Until 00:41:27 on Side B During Program; Crosstalk During Program
- Domestic Violence in the Jewish Community [1995-034], 1995-11-11; cuid33732 (Box 2, Audiocassette 718_0037)
  Duration: 1:03:09, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Static During Program
- Attica; W.H. Kunstler [1995-049], 1995-11-26; cuid33733 (Box 21, Reel 718_0929)
  Duration: 0:06:21, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; High Amount of Hiss During Program; Static During Program; Phasing During Program; High Background Noise During Program
- Michel Warschawski on Palestinians within Israel [1995-015], 1995-12-12; cuid33734 (Box 1, Audiocassette 718_0018)
  Duration: 0:31:30, Preservation Note: Side B is Blank; Phasing During Program; Program Distorted at Times
- Jewish Radio of the 40's and 50's [1995-035], 1995-12-31; cuid33735 (Box 2, Audiocassette 718_0038)
  Duration: 1:58:34, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Clicks and Pops During Program
- Teach-in Opening Plenary [1996-020], cuid33736 (Box 3, Audiocassette 718_0070)
  Duration: 1:40:08, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Program in Silence From 00:45:21 Until 00:46:34 on Side A During Program
- Teach-in 1 [1996-021], cuid33737 (Box 3, Audiocassette 718_0071)
  Duration: 1:01:41, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Static During Program; High Amount of Buzz During Program
- Teach-in 2 [1996-022], cuid33738 (Box 3, Audiocassette 718_0072)
  Duration: 1:29:07, Preservation Note: High Amount of Buzz During Program; Static During Program
- Teach-in 3 [1996-023], cuid33739 (Box 3, Audiocassette 718_0073)
  Duration: 0:53:17, Preservation Note: Phasing During Program; High Amount of Buzz During Program; Static During Program
- Teach-in 4 [1996-024], cuid33740 (Box 3, Audiocassette 718_0074)
  Duration: 0:57:36, Preservation Note: Static During Program; High Amount of Buzz During Program; Program Distorted at Times
- Teach-in 5 [1996-025], cuid33741 (Box 3, Audiocassette 718_0075)
  Duration: 0:55:47, Preservation Note: High Amount of Buzz During Program; Static During Program; Program Distorted at Times
- Teach-in 7 [1996-026], cuid33742 (Box 3, Audiocassette 718_0076)
  Duration: 1:01:10, Preservation Note: High Amount of Buzz During Program; Static During Program; Program Distorted at Times
- Teach-in 8 [1996-027], cuid33743 (Box 3, Audiocassette 718_0077)
  Duration: 0:55:35, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; Program in Silence From 00:04:14 Until 00:05:59 on Side A During Program; High Amount of Buzz During Program; Static During Program; Channel Imbalance
- Teach-in 9 [1996-028], cuid33744 (Box 3, Audiocassette 718_0078)
  Duration: 0:30:56, Preservation Note: Side B is Blank; Program Distorted at Times; High Amount of Buzz During Program; Static During Program
- Closing [1996-029], cuid33745 (Box 3, Audiocassette 718_0079)
  Duration: 0:06:50, Preservation Note: Side B is Blank; High Amount of Hiss During Program; Static During Program; Program Distorted at Times
- In Gerangl: End Police Brutality, Closing [1996-036], cuid33746 (Box 3, Audiocassette 718_0086)
  Duration: 1:29:12, Preservation Note: Program Distorted at Times; High Amount of Hiss During Program; Static During Program; Program in Silence From 00:34:00 Until 00:35:23 on Side A During Program
- Blood Libel [1996-040], cuid33747 (Box 3, Audiocassette 718_0088)
  Duration: 0:57:40, Preservation Note: Static During Program; Program Distorted at Times; Phasing During Program; High Amount of Hum During Program
- Police Brutality [2015-013], circa 1996-2014; cuid33748 (Box 11, Audiocassette 718_0383)